Ok tov. All right. שקט בבקשה *sheket bevakasha*. Today's דף daf *daf*
is what is today's דף daf *daf*? עין חת
*Ayin Chet*, right? What today's דף *daf* is עין חת *Ayin Chet*
and we are at the bottom of עין זין עמוד בית *Ayin
Zayin Amud Bet*. Actually today's דף *daf* is עין זין *Ayin Zayin*,
but we're דף *daf* ahead. So, okay, we're going to call it
עין חת *Ayin Chet*. So we now picked up with the first
wide line on עין זין עמוד בית *Ayin Zayin Amud Bet* and
as I said we are dealing with basic issues about הפרה hafara.
*Hafara* and התרה hatara *Hatara*. We had a great discussion the other
day about the fact that whether it's a בית דין beis din
*Beit Din*, yes, it needs three or three normal lay people or
one מומחה mumcheh *mumche*. We'll define that today, hopefully. But nevertheless, the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* points out about the many ways it's not like
a בית דין beis din. *Beit Din*. They can be standing, it
can be at night, it can be קרובים krovim, *krovim*. Partly the
question about sitting had to be a question about whether פותחין בחרטה
*potchin becharata* or not and whether it required ישוב הדעת *yishuv hadaat*,
but certainly in terms of formal aspects it's not like בית דין
beis din, *Beit Din*.
And that then raises the question where do you get the idea
that you need three, which we'll get to, but it really seems
that it is not considered a status of a בית דין beis
din *Beit Din*. And therefore that ties into issues about doing it
on שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos*, הפרה hafara *Hafara* you could do on שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos* because since you only have until the end of the
day, it's always a צורך *tzorech*, this is your last chance. התרה
hatara. *Hatara* can be done when it's done לצורך שבת Shabbos, *letshorech
Shabbos*, and because we said that it is not really an act
of בית דין beis din *Beit Din*, therefore you don't have to
דווקא *davka* do it by one, you can even do it with
three because even when you're doing it with three it's not really
an act of בית דין beis din *Beit Din*. So it is
a problem, you can't even do הפרה hafara, *Hafara* were it not
for the fact that there was a need, but when there is
a need, then it doesn't matter how you do it. Okay, so
again it can be done on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* when there's a
need, for הפרה hafara *Hafara* there's always a need and it really
is not a בית דין beis din. *Beit Din*, you can do
it with קרובים krovim. *krovim* and standing up and at night. Okay,
now we continue with basic issues of הפרה hafara, *Hafara* and התרה
hatara *Hatara* and the type of language that is needed. לא יאמר
אדם לאשתו *Lo yomar adam leishto*, a man should not say to
his wife, בשבת *beShabbos*,
on שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos* where he can be מיפר *meifer* because as
we said it's always a need, he should not say מופר ליכי
mufar lichi, בטול ליכי *mufar lichi batul lichi*, it is מופר mufar
*mufar* to you, it is בטול *batul* to you, כדרך שאומר לה
בחול *kederech sheomer lah bechol*, as you would say in a weekday.
So now we see that the standard language is I'm annulling it,
right? אלא אומר לה *Ella omer lah*, he should say to her,
טלי ואוכלי טלי ושתי *tli veochli tli vishasi*, take it and eat
it, take it and drink it, ונדר בטל batel מאליו *veneder batel
meilav* and that's good enough so you're not exactly directly using the
language of annulling again even though it's not a מעשה בית דין
beis din *maaseh Beit Din*, it is an act of like a
legal act of changing status through your sort of verbal act. And
therefore you should a little bit more imply it than exactly say
it. דבר davar, דבר davar *Daber davar*? Yeah, it's not exactly, I
wouldn't say דבר דבר *daber davar*, I would say it's not דבר
דבר *daber davar*, it's צורך שבת Shabbos, *tzorech Shabbos*, but I would
say more, I mean he's even eating and drinking it right now.
No, but I would say more because like I said
it's a legal type of an act. Okay, it's a verbal act
that affects the status of something.
ונדר בטל batel מאליו *Veneder batel meilav*, and the נדר neder, *neder*
is automatically בטל *batel*.
So which is important which A shows us the general language use
but also shows that you don't have to say it explicitly if
there's some issue like a שבת Shabbos, *Shabbos* issue that you want
to avoid. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר רבי יוחנן Amar
Rabbi Yochanan: וצריך שיבטל בלבו *Amar Rabbi Yochanan vetzarich sheyivatel belibo*, and
but what you have to do is it's not enough just to
say that, in your heart you have to think I am מבטל
mevatel, *mevatel* it, but the words you have to say don't have
to be words of ביטול bitul *bitul*. So that's going to be
interesting because that suggests that by the way וצריך שיבטל בלבו *vetzarich
sheyivatel belibo* should echo for some people in terms of פסח *Pesach*,
right? And if you're sort of you can't do a ביעור חמץ
*biyur chametz* and you're away or whatever you're מבטל בלבו mevatel belibo
ודיו *mevatel belibo vedaio*, okay, you מבטל *mevatel* in your heart so
it's interesting sort of think about those parallels. But anyway it sounds
like you don't need to have a verbal ביטול *bitul*, really it's
ultimately going on in the heart, but as the רן Ran *Ran*
says and as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will make it clear later
and as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* a little bit sort of indicated
before, you do need a verbal ביטול *bitul*. There's some interesting combination
taking place which which is totally inside your head which which presumably
would not work and saying words which are not words of ביטול
*bitul* but somehow in combination since they're implying ביטול *bitul* and you
have a ביטול *bitul* in your heart somehow in combination that works.
Okay, now let's take a look a little bit more and then
I'll explain a little bit more. תני תונא ברייתא braita: *Tanni tunah
braisa*, בית שמאי Beit Shammai אומרים *Beis Shammai omrim*, בית שמאי Beit
Shammai *Beis Shammai* says בשבת מבטל בלבו mevatel belibo. *beShabbos mevatel belibo*,
on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* you do like we said you do בלבו
*belibo*, the רן Ran *Ran* insists that בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beis
Shammai* means together with this indirect language, you do go ahead and
eat it and in your heart you think about ביטול *bitul*, that
type of a of a thing can work like we just said,
ובחול מוציא בשפתיו *ubechol motzi bisfasav*, but the weekday you have to
be more explicit and you have to say מופר ליכי mufar lichi,
בטול ליכי *mufar lichi batul lichi*. ובית הלל אומרים *Uveis Hillel omrim*,
בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* says אחד זה zeh ואחד זה
מבטל בלבו mevatel belibo. ואין צריך להוציא בשפתיו *echad ze veechad ze
mevatel belibo veein tzarich lehotzi bisfasav*, even during the weekday you don't
have to articulate. Now again you could read בית הלל Beit Hillel
*Beis Hillel* to mean you don't have to say anything, you just
do it in your head, that's what it sounds like but again
a later גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says very clearly that it's not enough
to
do it בלבו *belibo* for ביטול *bitul*. Okay, so wait. בית
הלל Beit Hillel says that even during the weekday, this is to
answer your question Michael, this type of thing can work. If it
can work on שבת, Shabbos it can work during the weekday. Okay,
and I mean, presumably בית שמאי Beit Shammai would also say that
בדיעבד bedi'avad it would work, but בית שמאי Beis Shammai would rather
you be more explicit when possible. And בית הלל Beit Hillel does
not demand that, and בית הלל Beit Hillel. says even implicitness is
okay as long as you're thinking about it. Again, the ר"ן Ran
says, it's not just thinking about it in your heart, it's thinking
about it in your heart and implicitly saying words which are doing
that implicitly.
And certainly if I said the מופר mufer ליכי, that takes care
of what's in my heart. Of course.
Yeah, that goes without... then obviously that's what you're saying.
But let's say I say, yeah, it's בטל in my heart.
Alright, so that goes about פיו ולבו שוין, piv velibo shavin, which
presumably would not work if we could actually prove that. Anyway, let
me just check the רמב"ם Rambam about this, which is י"ג yud
gimel נדרים Nedarim ז'. zayin. Hold on. See if the רמב"ם Rambam
agrees with the ר"ן Ran on this, which I did not have
a chance to check. המפר נדרי
בתו או אשתו צריך להוציא בשפתיו ואם הפר בלבו אינו מופר אבל
המבטל אין
לו צריך להוציא בשפתיו אלא מבטל בלבו בלבד וכופל אותו לעשות בין
עשה בין לא עשה בטל הנדר. Hamefer nidrei
bito o ishto tzarich lehotzi bisfatav ve'im hefer belibo eino mufar aval
hamvatel ein
lo tzarich lehotzi bisfatav ela mevatel belibo bilvad vekhofel oto la'asot bein
asa bein lo asa batel haneder. What? Difference
between...
whoa, there's a weird רמב"ם. Rambam.
Okay, I have to look at the רמב"ם. Rambam. There's a very
interesting רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam says, wait a minute, המפר נדרי
אשתו בשבת בין בזה ובין בזה לא צריך לומר לה בשבת מופר
ליכי כדרך שהיה אומר לה בחול אלא מבטל בלבו ואומר לה. Hamefer
nidrei ishto beShabbat bein bezeh uvein bezeh lo tzarich lomar lah beShabbat
mufar lichi kederech shehayah omer lah bechol ela mevatel belibo ve'amar lah.
Okay, so first of all, he says like the ר"ן Ran that
when it says... well, like the גמרא, Gemara that you're מבטל בלבו
plus the אכלי ליכי שתי ליכי ושישי ליכי. achli lichi shtichi veshisichi.
But he actually has
a difference between being מפר mefer and being מבטל, right? So that
was a double language here: מופר mufer, ליכי,
בטל ליכי. batel lichi. The רמבם Rambam sees them as two separate
processes. So I have to look at the רמב"ם Rambam more. But
okay, but he basically agrees with the ר"ן Ran that again, that
you know, it's a combination of ביטול בלבו bittul belibo and saying
something indirect. Yes.
If you're given a special permission because it's שבת, Shabbos? that consideration,
why should it apply during the week when you don't need the
special consideration?
Well right, so בית... that's what בית שמאי Beis Shammai says. And
בית הלל Beit Hillel would presumably say it's like not a special
consideration. I mean, if it works, it works. Right? בית שמאי Beis
Shammai would frame it as a special consideration. On שבת, Shabbos. meaning
בית הלל Beis Hillel would say like this: on שבת Shabbos we
demand that you be indirect. We don't allow you to be direct.
But during the weekday, whether direct or indirect, either way works. So
why should I care which way you do it? That's בית הלל.
Beis Hillel Right. You know, so right, everybody agrees that you must
do it this way on שבת. Shabbos. The idea is that are
you allowed to do it that... and בית שמאי Beis Shammai would
rather you be direct and בית הלל Beis Hillel says as long
as it works, what do I care? Okay. Now I want to
say something about the language because the ר"ן Ran asks the following
question. The גמרא Gemorah earlier, not yesterday we did two days ago,
anyway the גמרא Gemorah earlier if you remember said, it was just
two lines above, says האומר לאשתו קונם נדרים שתדורי אי אפשי שתדורי,
ha'omer le'ishto konam nedarim shetiduri i efshi shetiduri, you know, "I don't
want you to make those vows," אין זה נדר ein ze neder
or "this is not a vow," לא אמר כלום. lo amar klum.
He didn't say anything. So the ר"ן Ran's says, I don't get
it, we just said that you could be indirect by הפרה. hafara,
Meaning, the reason the ר"ן Ran said, you know, earlier that it
didn't work is he said you had to be explicit. To say
"this is not a vow" is not saying "I am annulling it."
Okay, but here we said that you don't have to be explicit
as long as you're מבטל בלבו. Okay, so why didn't that work,
that earlier language of "this is not a vow"? So the ר"ן's
Ran. answer seems to be, well, you said "this is not a
vow" but you weren't מבטל בלבו. It's like, what? Like, what do
you mean then? I would suggest something else. I would say that
even when you're being implicit and indirect, it has to be clear
what you're being implicit about. If I say, think about the difference
if I say "go ahead and eat it." How could you now...
what's implicit in that? "How could you tell me go ahead and
eat it? I made a vow." So the implicit thing is, the
only way my husband could be telling me "go ahead and eat
it" is if he annulled the vow, right? So telling me "go
ahead and eat it" is implicitly saying "I have annulled the vow."
But let's say instead of my husband saying "go ahead and eat
it," my husband said "that is not a vow." Now, "that is
not a vow" is different. "That is not a vow" is, is
it, it was a vow and I annulled it? It's a statement
of fact: "it's not a vow." But you're wrong, it is a
vow, right? So it's not saying "I am making it not a
vow," it's just saying "it isn't." It's a wrong description. Okay, or
if he says "I don't want you to make a vow." Very
nice you don't want me to do it, but now I did
it. What's the story of it? Maybe he says "I don't want
you to do it and just to spite you I'm not going
to annul it," right? So saying I don't want or saying it's
not a vow is not as implicit that I'm annulling it as
saying go ahead and eat. Okay? So that I think is the
real difference, the ר"ן Ran doesn't say it. So you have to
be, you don't have to be explicit, you could be implicit, but
not every language is implicitly an annulment. Saying I really wish you
hadn't done that, I am so angry that you did that is
still not telling me whether you're going to annul it or not.
So I really think, so it is important. A, it's enough to
do ביטול בלב bitul baleiv and an, and a statement that's, that's
implicit, but it has to be clear what it's being implicit about.
You had a question, Michael?
Yeah, so, I was trying to understand, when we said in the
very beginning, מופר ליכי בטיל ליכי, mufar lichi batil lichi, you have
to say both or does one of those two things work?
No, either. But the רמב"ם, Rambam, interestingly, I have to get back
to the רמב"ם Rambam about the difference between הפרה hafara, and ביטול
because I, I, I've forgotten about that. I have to look into
that. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemorah says like this. אמר רבי
יוחנן: Rabbi Yochanan חכם שאמר בלשון בעל ובעל שאמר בלשון חכם לא
אמר כלום. Chacham she-amar bi-leshon ba'al u-ba'al she-amar bi-leshon chacham lo amar
klum. If one of them tries to use the language of the
other, okay, so it's clear that if the חכם chacham tries to
do the act of the בעל, ba'al, the חכם chacham says I'm
annulling it and he really wants to annul it rather than being
מתיר, matir, or the husband says I'm מתירing matir it and he's
trying to do התרה hatara? rather than, rather than, rather than הפרה,
hafara. they can't do the other person's process, right? One has the
right to annul, the other has the right to assess and inquire
and and and מתיר matir it based on the fact that it
never existed. Well, I guess the חכם chacham can מתיר matir though.
Okay fine, if he's a מומחה mumcheh. fine because it's קרוב, karov,
right, good. Okay, anyway, but let's say they know what they're doing
but they use the wrong language, okay? I know I'm annulling, but
in my act of annulling I am saying מותר לך, mutar lach,
מותר ליכי, mutar lichi, okay, but in my, but the process I'm
trying to do is the process of annulling. Or the חכם chacham
is doing a process of התרה. hatara He says, so if you
had known, would you have wanted? No, I wouldn't have wanted, da
da da da, we've decided that there was חרטה charata or whatever,
there was a פתח petach and therefore I said מופר לך. mufar
lach. So I used the wrong language. I was trying to do
the right process but I used the other one's language. What's the
story? So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said: חכם שאמר בלשון בעל ובעל
שאמר בלשון חכם. Chacham she-amar bi-leshon ba'al u-ba'al she-amar bi-leshon chacham.
If you use the language of the other one, לא אמר כלום,
lo amar klum, it doesn't work. Okay, and this is again showing
the importance of actually, you know, it's not just what you wanted
to do, something has to be articulated. So we said it doesn't
have to be explicit what you're doing, but you do have to
articulate and here, if you articulate the wrong concept, then it does
not work. Okay? דתניא, De-tanya, as we taught: זה הדבר, זה הדבר
zeh hadavar zeh hadavar, אשר צוה ה'. That's in the beginning of
מטות Mattot where it speaks, spells out the laws of נדרים, nedarim,
right? And he speaks אל ראשי המטות לאמר זה הדבר אשר צוה
ה' איש כי ידר נדר,
el rashei ha-mattot leimor zeh ha-davar asher tzivah Hashem
ish ki yidor neder, right? או השבע שבועה לאסר אסר על נפשו.
o hishava shevuah le-esor issar al nafsho. This, meaning exactly this way.
חכם מתיר ואין בעל מתיר. Chacham matir ve-ein ba'al matir. So it's
only the חכם chacham can do the act of התרה hatara, and
not the husband. Of course, it's so funny, where did it mention
in the פרשה parsha that a חכם chacham does התרה? hatara? But
somehow we are going to infer that from the ראשי המטות rashei
ha-mattot that a חכם chacham does התרה hatara, and זה says everybody
does only what they're supposed to do, not the other person's job.
שיכול, She-yachol, because we could make a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה
חכם שאין מיפר מתיר, U-mah chacham she-ein meifer matir, that a חכם
chacham who can't do הפרה hafara can do התרה, hatara so בעל
שמיפר, ba'al she-meifer, a בעל ba'al that can do הפרה, hafarah, that
can do an annulment, אינו דין שמתיר, eino din she-matir, a fortiori
should he be able to do התרה? hatara, Because he has a
power the חכם chacham doesn't have, so he should certainly have the
power the חכם chacham does have. It's a little bit ironic because
he has their unique power. But anyway, תלמוד לומר זה הדבר. Talmud
lomar zeh ha-davar. No, this is the matter. חכם מתיר, Chacham matir,
only the חכם chacham can do the התרה, hatara, ואין בעל מתיר,
ve-ein ba'al matir, not the בעל. ba'al. Now we're going to say
the reverse. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we taught another ברייתא: braisa זה
הדבר, Zeh ha-davar, this is the matter. בעל מיפר, Ba'al meifer,
only the בעל ba'al can do הפרה, hafara, annulment, ואין חכם מיפר,
ve-ein chacham meifer, and the חכם chacham cannot do an annulment. שיכול,
She-yachol, because I could make a קל וחומר. kal va-chomer. ומה בעל
שאין מתיר מיפר, U-mah ba'al she-ein matir meifer, the husband that we've
just proven cannot do a התרה hatara can do a הפרה, חכם
שמתיר, chacham she-matir, the חכם chacham that has a power the husband
doesn't have, he can do a התרה, hatara אינו דין שיפר, eino
din she-yafer, a fortiori should he have the power the husband has,
that he should annul? תלמוד לומר זה הדבר. Talmud lomar zeh ha-davar.
No, this way. בעל מיפר ואין חכם מיפר. Ba'al meifer ve-ein chacham
meifer. Only the בעל ba'al can do an annulment, not the חכם.
chacham. Each one can only do their own sphere. Now again, this
does not exactly prove רבי יוחנן's point, right? This proves that the
actual act has to be, one has to be an act of
התרה, hatara. the other an act of הפרה. Does it prove that
one cannot say that like sort of like a יד לנדר? yad
la-neder? You know, we remember we learned way at the beginning that
if I say like a נדר, neder, I won't go to the
baseball game today, which is a complete mixing of two ideas, right?
We, some ראשונים rishonim say that's still like a יד לשבועה. yad
la-shevuah. Even though I said נדר, neder, it's clear that I really
wanted to make a שבועה, shevuah, so it's like I made a
שבועה. shevuah. Okay? So just because a חכם chacham has the process
of התרה hatara and the בעל ba'al has the process of הפרה
does not prove that if you try to do your right thing
but you use the slightly wrong language, that it wouldn't be
effective, right? Since they are doing, since they are fundamentally doing different
processes, the language is technically refers to a different process and therefore
it does not work. We can't even say you're implicitly or a
יד yad or whatever, it does not work if you use the
other person's language.
I think the ראש Rosh says too that the דבר, the דיבור...
deebur...
Oh, that's a nice point, I hadn't thought about that. But the
דבר point emphasizes that the fact that it's really the דיבור. deebur.
That's a nice point. Okay. Okay.
Fine.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemorah says like this, one minute. Yeah,
so take a look at the רן. Ran The רן Ran says,
how do we know that the language of a חכם chacham is
מותר, mutar, right? The language of the husband being מופר mufer is
in the תורה, Torah, right? ואם הפר יפר אותה מאישה. v'im hafer
yafer osa me'ishah.
But how do we know what the language of the חכם chacham
is? So if you look at the רן Ran at the bottom
here ע"ז ע"ב, ayin zayin amud bet, he says like this: בעל
מפורש בכתוב דהיינו לשון הפרה, ba'al meforash b'katuv de-haynu lashon hafara, ולשון
חכם דהוי מותר לך משמע ליה מדכתיב לא יחל דברו, v'lashon chacham
d'avei mutar lach mashma lei mi-dechtiv lo yachel devaro,
right?
That's how we learn out the role of the חכם. chacham. You
cannot make your words sort of, you know, void. לא יעשה דבריו
חולין. lo ya'aseh devarav chullin.
You cannot make them... what would be a word here for חולין...
chullin... not like
desecrated... that's not a good word. Anyway, but insignificant. ודרשינן אבל אחרים
מחללין לו שעושין אותו חולין, u-darsinan aval acherim mechalelin lo, she-osin oso
chullin, and בחולין b'chullin
if something was never sort of sanctified or of weight, מותר שייך
למימר ביה. mutar shayach l'meimar beih. So the language of מותר mutar
is relevant. That's not very persuasive. Okay, you're calling it חולין, chullin,
so מותר. mutar. Anyway, so that's his first answer. That's how we
know a language of מותר. mutar. But then at the top of
ע"ח ayin chet it says, ובירושלמי משמע דחכם נמי מצי אמר אין
כאן נדר אין כאן שבועה. u-v'Yerushalmi mashma de-chacham nami matzi amar ein
kan neder ein kan shvu'a.
That a חכם chacham can say, remember what we said the בעל
ba'al cannot say, אין כאן נדר, ein kan neder, it is not
a נדר, neder that doesn't work for a בעל. ba'al. Because for
a בעל ba'al it was a נדר neder and he's now just
annulling it. אין כאן נדר ein kan neder is saying it never
was a vow. But who can say that? The חכם. chacham. Because
that's what the חכם chacham is doing. He's making it like it
never existed, right? דגרסינן התם בעל שאמר בלשון חכם וחכם שאמר בלשון
בעל לא אמר כלום אלא זה אומר כיוחו של זה וזה אומר
כיוחו של זה. d'garsinan hatam ba'al she-amar b'lashon chacham v'chacham she-amar b'lashon
ba'al lo amar klum ela zeh omer kiyucho shel zeh v'zeh omer
kiyucho shel zeh. הבעל אומר מופר לך, ha-ba'al omer mufer lach, right?
That it's annulled, because it existed and now it's annulled. והזקן אומר
אין כאן נדר אין כאן שבועה. v'ha-zaken omer ein kan neder ein
kan shvu'a. Okay, ולפי זה משמע ליה, u-l'fi zeh mashma lei, so
if it's saying it doesn't exist is the language of the חכם
chacham because
that's
what he's doing, therefore
that's how we get the idea of מותר. mutar. לישנא דמפר שייך
מכאן ולהבא. lishnah d'mefir shayach mikan u-leha'ba.
מפר mefir means I am annulling it from here moving forward and
that's the language of the בעל... ba'al... לישנא דמותר בדבר שהיה מותר
מעיקרא. lishnah d'mutar b'davar she-hayah mutar mei-ikara. If I say it's מותר,
mutar, if somebody asks me a שאלה shaila or a rabbi, what's
the story with doing this on שבת, Shabbos what's the story with
this chicken, what's the story with this, and I say it's מותר,
mutar, it doesn't mean I am now magically making it מותר mutar
because I have the power to hand out dispensations and turn something
that's אסור assur into מותר. mutar. It means it's always been מותר.
mutar. Okay, so the רן Ran, says the language of מותר לך
mutar lach means that it was always permissible. And therefore it's just
like, therefore
the חכם chacham cannot say it's מופר because that means it was
a נדר neder, and only from here on in. He can say
מותר, mutar, he can say אין כאן נדר. ein kan neder. The
husband can only say מופר, he can't say מותר, mutar, he can't
say אין כאן נדר, ein kan neder, and that goes back to
what we said earlier, that the husband cannot say אין כאן נדר.
ein kan neder. Okay, so is that clear? אין כאן נדר ein
kan neder and מותר mutar mean it never existed. That's only the
חכם, chacham, that's why it doesn't work if the husband says it.
מופר means מכאן ולהבא. mikan u-leha'ba. Which by the way is exactly
the language we say in התרת נדרים hataras nedarim that we do
on ערב ראש השנה, erev Rosh Hashanah, right? Because what do we
say...
first, what do we say before we get to the אין כאן?
ein kan? We say מותר לך, מותר לך, מותר לך, mutar lach,
mutar lach, mutar lach, right?
I don't think we
say מותר לך, mutar lach,
I don't think they actually have that. Do they?
Hold on, where is it here?
They say הכל מותר לך, הכל שרוי לך, hakol mutar lach, hakol
sharui lach, 762.
Oh, הכל מותר לך. hakol mutar lach. So we do say מותר,
mutar, fine, okay, fine. 762. Why
does it come after סוכות Sukkos here? I don't know, okay, fine.
הכל יהיו מותרים לך, הכל מחולים
לך, הכל שרויים לך. hakol yi-yu mutarin lach, hakol mechulin lach, hakol
shruyin lach. So מותר mutar and שרוי, sharui, שרוי sharui is the
Aramaic for מותר. mutar. מחול machul is an interesting phrase because מחול
machul sounds a little more like הופר. hufar. Like when you're מוחל
mocheil a debt, the debt existed and now you're erasing it. Right?
אין כאן לא נדר ולא שבועה ולא נזירות ולא חרם ולא איסור
ולא קונם. ein kan lo neder v'lo shvu'a v'lo nezirus v'lo cherem
v'lo issur v'lo konam. It doesn't exist. Okay, so it has מותר
mutar and it has שרוי sharui which is the same as מותר
mutar and it has אין כאן. ein kan. And מחולים לך mechulin
lach is interesting, it'd be interesting to find out like whether that
was originally
in the נוסח. nusach. Maybe it has to do with the fact
that like if somebody transgressed their vow that even though retroactively
the בית דין beis din
annulled it, maybe it requires.
Whatever it is, however he conjugates that. Yeah, does that work too?
Well, it depends what יני yani means, because יני yani according to
the English I was looking at says that it's referring to her
and not to the vow. If he refuse, what, right, what does
it say there?
In your translation, it's translated as restrains, restrains her, right?
Or so that's about her, that's not about the vow. What you
do is an act to the vow. Okay. Fine. So we have
the idea that it's different languages, and different languages reflecting very different
processes, and התנא דהכא hatanna de-hacha retroactive, and therefore you can't use
the other person's. Now the ברייתא braisa continues: נאמר כאן זה הדבר
ונאמר להלן זה הדבר. ne'emar kan zeh hadavar vene'emar lehalan zeh hadavar.
It says here and it says later zeh hadavar. Okay, where's later?
It says it by שחוטי חוץ. sh'chutei chutz. בשחוטי חוץ, besh'chutei chutz,
by slaughtering a sanctified animal outside the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. מה
בשחוטי חוץ אהרן ובניו וכל ישראל, mah besh'chutei chutz Aharon u-vanav ve-chol
Yisrael, the same way by שחוטי חוץ sh'chutei chutz it says דבר
אל אהרן ואל בניו ואל כל בני ישראל. daber el Aharon ve-el
banav ve-el kol b'nei Yisrael. Right, it says explicitly this applies to
Aharon and his sons and all בני ישראל, b'nei Yisrael, I mean
Aharon and his sons because it's about כהנים kohanim and bringing קרבנות,
korbanos, but everybody because if somebody brings a קרבן korban outside the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, so I mean it applies to all ישראל.
Yisrael. אף פרשת נדרים, af parshas nedarim, even in נדרים, nedarim, אהרן
ובניו וכל ישראל Aharon u-vanav ve-chol Yisrael applies to all of ישראל,
Yisrael, not just ראשי המטות. rashei hamatos. So, ומה כאן ראשי המטות,
u-mah kan rashei hamatos, by נדרים nedarim it emphasizes the head of
the tribes, so אף להלן ראשי המטות, af lehalan rashei hamatos, so
similarly by שחוטי חוץ sh'chutei chutz the head of the tribes. Now,
what does this mean? Why by פרשת נדרים parshas nedarim are we
emphasizing all of Israel? And why, I mean obviously they're all of
the laws of איש איש כי ידור נדר, ish ish ki yidor
neder, it talks about any person who makes a vow, and why
by שחוטי חוץ sh'chutei chutz are we talking about ראשי המטות? rashei
hamatos? So let's see what the גמרא Gemorah says. בפרשת נדרים למאי
הלכתא, b'parshas nedarim le-mai hilchesa, for what purpose in נדרים nedarim are
we emphasizing that it applies to all ישראל? Yisrael? אמר רב אחא
בר יעקב להכשיר שלושה הדיוטות. amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov lehachshir shlosha
hedyotos. Okay, so this is where we get the idea that it
does not have to be a ראשי המטות, rashei hamatos, that there's
these two levels of who can do the התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim.
ראשי המטות rashei hamatos tells us, I mean again, remember the פרשה
parsha is always about הפרה, it's always about a father and a
husband, but nevertheless we learn out from לא יחל דברו lo yachel
devaro that there's an act of a חכם chacham to מתיר, matir,
and ראשי המטות rashei hamatos tells us that it's a person of
status, of stature, okay, who's מתיר, matir, which is going to be
the idea of a מומחה. mumcheh Okay, so we understand that a
יחיד מומחה yachid mumcheh can מתיר. matir. But the idea that that
role also applies to כל ישראל kol Yisrael tells us there's a
second rule, there's a second
category of a layperson that can be מתיר, matir, and in order
to make sense, well what is it, is it a מומחה mumcheh
or a layperson, we have to say, ah, one מומחה mumcheh, but
three laypeople. Now the ר"ן Ran does say, again, like where did
you get three, right? How did you get that number? So he
says, well once it can't be one because we know one is
only for this מומחה, mumcheh, person of status, the next logical number
is three because that's like a בית דין. beis din Now again,
what does that mean? I mean if the idea before was that
it's not a בית דין, beis din. it can be at night,
it can be קרובים, etc., what is the significance of three? So
what I would suggest here is a point that Rav Soloveitchik says
in a number of places, which is, you know,
which is that בית דין beis din does not always function as
an adjudicating body. If you think about like the סנהדרין Sanhedrin that
goes out in the case of the עגלה ערופה eglah arufah and
says ידינו לא שפכו את הדם הזה, yadeinu lo shafchu es hadam
hazeh, they're not adjudicating anything, they're like representing the Jewish people, right?
So, or like when a בית דין beis din. makes the new
month, you know, the leap year, right? They're not really adjudicating, they're
sort of speaking there as representatives of the Jewish people. So if
understood that way, you can understand ראשי המטות rashei hamatos is a
leadership role, right? It's not, it's not a דיין dayan role, it's
a leadership role, and as such another institution that represents a type
of a leadership capacity for the people is the institution of בית
דין beis din as a representative leadership of the people. So if
it's not a person, you know, in the person's stature, it can
be the institution of the בית דין. beis din But that could
explain why it could be at night and standing and whatever, because
it's not in their role as דיינים, dayanim, it's in their role
as, you know, as sort of leaders or as representatives. It's also,
I think it's to be tied into words in the תורה. Torah.
Like the תורה Torah sometimes refers to the בית דין beis din.
as זקנים, zekenim, sometimes as like שופטים, shoftim,
אלהים, Elohim, right? Which is more adjudicating and so on, and sometimes
as זקנים, zekenim, the זקנים zekenim were the leaders of the people.
Okay, so that's what I think is where we get this idea
that it's a בית דין beis din, in the capacity of ראשי
המטות, rashei hamatos, and therefore it's three, but maybe it does not
have those requirements before and it's not considered an act of בית
דין beis din as an adjudicating type of an act. Okay, so
that's what we get from that idea that there's something that rules
that can be מתיר matir that's not a single ראש המטה, rosh
hamateh, you know, leader, and that's a בית דין.
beis din And what's אהרן ובניו, Aharon u-vanav, what does he have
to do with this?
Nothing. It's just that that was the, we learned from the other
thing that it's everybody, really doesn't mean אהרן ובניו, Aharon u-vanav, it
really is getting to כל ישראל. kol Yisrael. Okay. Now, והא ראשי
המטות כתיב? ve-ha rashei hamatos kesiv? But okay, how do you say
for הדיוטות hedyotos it says ראשי המטות? rashei hamatos? אמר רב חסדא
ואיתימא רבי יוחנן ביחיד מומחה. amar Rav Chisda ve-isima Rabbi Yochanan beyachid
mumcheh. Yes, ראשי המטות, rashei hamatos, if you're a יחיד yachid and
you're a מומחה, mumcheh, an expert—we'll discuss what that means in a
minute, let's finish the סוגיא—then sugya one is enough. But if you're
not of the stature of a מומחה, mumche. then three. I'm sorry,
how do you get that from ראשי המטות? rashei hamatos? Maybe it
means you need all
of them? Yeah but it doesn't give a number I don't know.
I mean I don't know what to say. Okay how do you
know who's a ראש המטה? Rosh HaMateh? This רש"י Rashi says it's
always the נשיא, Nasi, I don't know. Anyway fine. I don't know
what to say Michael. Moving on. Okay. ראשי המטות בשחוטי חוץ למאי
הלכתא? Rashei Hamatos b'shchutei chutz l'mai hilchasa? So what's the role of
ראשי המטות Rashei Hamatos by שחוטי חוץ? shchutei chutz? What does being
a קרבן korban outside the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash have to do
with ראשי המטות? Rashei Hamatos? So the גמרא Gemorah says אמר רב
ששת לומר שיש
שאלה בהקדש Amar Rav Sheshes lomar sheyesh she'eila b'hekdesh that there's a
role that ראשי המטות Rashei Hamatos could play by שחוטי חוץ. shchutei
chutz. What role could they play? Here's a great way to get
out of a terrible עבירה. aveira. You slaughtered a קרבן korban outside
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're חייב כרת. chayav kareis. So what
you do is you go to the חכם Chacham and you say:
Had I been thinking about A, B, and C, I would never
have made the animal הקדש. hekdesh. And then the חכם Chacham is
מתיר matir it. In the same way a חכם Chacham can מתיר
matir a נדר, neder he can מתיר matir a הקדש. hekdesh. Okay
and therefore retroactively I just slaughtered a חולין chullin animal outside the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so I didn't do the עבירה aveira at
all. So that's why ראשי המטות Rashei Hamatos can play a role
in שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz because they can actually be undo, they
can play, it's the role of like being מתיר matir a נדר
neder and they can undo it. So the גמרא Gemara says
ולבית שמאי דאמרי
אין שאלה בהקדש u'l'Beis Shammai d'amri ein she'eila b'hekdesh that there's no
שאלה she'eila in הקדש, hekdesh, you can't undo הקדש, hekdesh, ראשי המטות
דכתיבי בשחוטי חוץ למאי הלכתא? Rashei Hamatos d'chsivi b'shchutei chutz l'mai hilchasa?
So for what purpose, what role would they play? They're only according
to בית הלל because there's a debate בית הלל בית שמאי. Beis
Hillel Beis Shammai. Let's say I'm מקדיש makdish something by accident. I
said the wrong words out of my mouth, I didn't want to
be מקדיש makdish it but I was מקדיש makdish it. So בית
הלל says, okay it's not a הקדש. hekdesh. And בית שמאי Beis
Shammai says even if you do it in error, בטעות, b'to'us, it's
still הקדש. hekdesh. And since the whole role of doing התרת נדרים
hataras nedarim works by defining something to be בטעות b'to'us in error,
right? So therefore בית הלל says so it works by הקדש, hekdesh,
it makes it a הקדש טעות hekdesh to'us and הקדש טעות hekdesh
to'us doesn't take effect. But בית שמאי says even הקדש טעות hekdesh
to'us is binding. So בית שמאי says there's no התרה hatara, by
הקדש. hekdesh. So according to בית שמאי there's no role for the
ראשי המטות Rashei Hamatos by שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. What do you
do by the גזירה שוה? gezeira shava? למאי הלכתא? l'mai hilchasa? So
the גמרא Gemara says
לית להו גזירה שוה. leis lehu gezeira shava. They don't hold of
the גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. Alright, but now we have to figure
out if they don't hold of the גזירה שוה gezeira shava what
about the idea of three הדיוטות? hedyotos? That was really what we
were out to learn, that you could do three הדיוטות hedyotos for
התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. So the גמרא Gemara says זה הדבר בפרשת
נדרים למאי כתיב? zeh hadavar b'parshas nedarim l'mai ksiv? So first of
all why does it say זה הדבר? Zeh ha-davar, It's not to
make the גזירה שוה, gezeira shava, it's not to link it to
שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. So the גמרא Gemara says that we've already
answered. לומר חכם מתיר ואין בעל מתיר בעל מיפר ואין חכם מיפר
lomar chacham matir v'ein ba'al matir ba'al meifer v'ein chacham meifer to
tell you what we've already said. זה הדבר zeh hadavar? is not
to link it to שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz but to tell you
the בעל ba'al does what he does, הפרה, and the חכם Chacham
does what he does, התרה. Okay but now the more important
question: זה הדבר בשחוטי חוץ למאי כתיב? zeh hadavar b'shchutei chutz l'mai
ksiv? What's זה הדבר zeh hadavar by שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz teaching
you if again it's not to link it to the case of
התרת נדרים? hataras nedarim? So לומר lomar to tell you על שחיטה
חייב ואין חייב על מליקה. al shechita chayav v'ein chayav al melika.
Only on this,
זה הדבר. zeh hadavar It's שוחט מחוץ למחנה, shocheit min chutz l'machaneh,
slaughters an animal as a sacrifice. But if it's a bird sacrifice
and you do מליקה melika with the fingernail, even though that's very
similar to שחיטה, shechita, you're not חייב. chayav. Okay. So בית שמאי
doesn't make a גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. זה הדבר zeh hadavar. teaches
you, you know, for each thing a certain הלכה halacha that only
a חכם Chacham can do what he can do, only a בעל
ba'al can do what he can do, only for שחיטה shechita not
for other things. Fine. They're not linked. So they're not linked because
you cannot do התרה by הקדש. hekdesh. Fine. But back to the
question, where do you know the idea of
three הדיוטות, hedyotos, three laypeople for התרת נדרים? hataras nedarim?
No, let's just
finish it.
Okay. אלא בית שמאי להכשיר ג' הדיוטות מנלן? ela Beis Shammai l'hachshir
gimel hedyotos minalan? Where do you know three laypeople? נפקא להו מדרב
אסי בר נתן. nafka lehu mi'deRav Assi bar Nasn. A different source,
רב אסי בר נתן. Rav Assi bar Nasn. דכתיב
וידבר משה את מועדי ה' אל בני ישראל. d'chsiv Vayidabeir Moshe es
mo'adei Hashem el bnei Yisrael. משה Moshe spoke the מועדים mo'adim of
God to בני ישראל. bnei Yisrael. ותניא בברייתא v'tanya b'raisa רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר: Rabbi Yosei HaGlili omer: מועדי נאמרו ולא נאמרה שבת בראשית
עמהם. mo'adei ne'emru v'lo ne'emra Shabbos b'reishis imahem. In this פרשה, parsha,
מועדי ה', mo'adei Hashem, it talks about the מועדים mo'adim not שבת,
Shabbos. which is crazy. What? ולא נאמרה שבת
בראשית עמהם. v'lo ne'emra Shabbos b'reishis imahem. But of course it does,
right there in אמור, Emor, it starts with אלה מועדי ה' eileh
mo'adei Hashem and then שבת Shabbos is the first thing, ששת ימים.
sheshes yamim. Why is שבת included in the מועדים? mo'adim? So we'll
see about that. And רבי אומר: Rebbi omer: מועדי נאמרו, mo'adei ne'emru,
it's talking about
the מועדים, mo'adim, ולא נאמרה פרשת נדרים עמהם. v'lo ne'emra parshas nedarim
imahem. Not פרשת נדרים. parshas nedarim.
Now that's a little bizarre, but back then you're thinking about אמור,
Emor, but where else do the מועדים mo'adim occur? Where else do
the מועדים mo'adim occur? Michael? פנחס. Pinchas. What פרשה parsha occurs right
after פנחס? Pinchas? מטות. Matos. So the פרשה parsha right after the
מועדים mo'adim in פנחס Pinchas is about the נדרים. nedarim. So he's
saying oh this is only about the מועדים, mo'adim, not about נדרים.
nedarim. Okay, like what point is being made? It's very unclear what
point is being made. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara, says.
So רב אסי בר נתן קשיא ליה הא מתניתא, Rav Assi bar
Nasn kasha lei ha matnisa, רב אסי בר נתן Rav Assi bar
Nasn didn't understand what this ברייתא braita was talking about. רב אשי
בר נתן קשיא ליה המתניתא, Rav Ashi bar Nassan kashle hamatnita, רב
אשי בר נתן Rav Ashi bar Nassan didn't understand what this ברייתא
braita was talking about. אזל לנהרדעא, azal l'Naharda'ah, he went to נהרדעא
Naharda'ah לקמיה דרב ששת, l'kamei d'Rav Sheshet, in front of רב ששת.
Rav Sheshet. ולא אשכחיה, v'lo ashkechei, he couldn't find רב ששת. Rav
Sheshet. אתא בתריה למחוזא, ata batrei l'Mechuza, so he followed him to
מחוזא. Mechuza.
He followed רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, right? He went to נהרדעא, Naharda'ah,
no, and he wasn't in נהרדעא, Naharda'ah, he was expecting him in
נהרדעא Naharda'ah and somebody told him, oh, he went to מחוזא, Mechuza,
and so he's there, okay. שמעתי אמינא מחוזא. shamati amina Mechuza. All
right, anyway, אמר ליה, amar lei, so anyway then he found him
and he said, here's what the ברייתא braita? means. מועדי ה' נאמרו
ולא נאמר שבת בראשית עמהם. moadei Hashem ne'emru v'lo ne'emar Shabbos Bereishit
imahem. I know I'm saying this was the question. He said to
him, what do you mean מועדי ה' moadei Hashem and it doesn't
say שבת? והכתיב שבת והכתיב שבת עמהם! vehaketiv Shabbos vehaketiv Shabbos imahem!
In the פרשה parsha it says
שבת. ותו מועדי ה' נאמרו ולא נאמר פרשת נדרים עמהם. v'su moadei
Hashem ne'emru v'lo ne'emar parshat nedarim imahem. It says מועדי ה' moadei
Hashem and it doesn't say the נדרים nedarim with them. והא מסיטרא
כתיבא, v'ha misitra kesiva, it's written right by the side of it,
right? סטרא sitra is anybody who's ever learned any any קבלה, Kabbalah,
you know, about the סטרא אחרא, sitra achra, the other side, going
over to the other side, the dark side of the force. Anyway,
so it says right there next to it. It says נדרים nedarim
right after פנחס. Pinchas. What do you mean it's not said with
them? What's the point of this ברייתא? braita הכי קתני, hachi katani,
this is what the ברייתא means.
מועדי ה' צריכים קידוש בית דין. moadei Hashem tzrichim kiddush beis din.
שבת בראשית אין צריכה קידוש בית דין. Shabbos Bereishit ein tzricha kiddush
beis din. It says אלה מועדי ה' אשר תקראו אותם במועדם. elei
moadei Hashem asher tikre'u otam bemoadam. These are the מועדים moadim that
you, you will call them, you declare the מועדים. moadim. How do
you declare the מועדים? moadim? Because you declare what ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh is. בית דין beis din sanctifies the new moon. So מועדי
ה' moadei Hashem requires the sanctification of בית דין. beis din שבת
בראשית אין צריכה קידוש בית דין. Shabbos Bereishit ein tzricha kiddush beis
din. בית דין beis din doesn't need to sanctify the week and
every week decide which day is Sunday. Okay, or maybe you could
even say even without that, even if you don't say make קידוש
kiddush or no certainly no בית דין beis din makes קידוש, kiddush,
שבת is still שבת. שבת has its sanctity without בית דין. beis
din. Okay, so it's a little unclear why you need a פסוק
pasuk to tell you that, like what would have been the הוה
אמינא? hava amina? But anyway, that's the point. אשר תקראו אותם במועדם
asher tikre'u otam bemoadam goes only on the מועדים, moadim, not on
שבת. Similarly, מועדי ה' צריכים מומחה. moadei Hashem tzrichim mumche. מועדי ה'
moadei Hashem because they are the new month is sanctified by בית
דין, beis din right? That requires a בית דין beis din of
מומחים, mumchim, of experts. Only they can sanctify the new moon. ואין
פרשת נדרים צריכה מומחה. v'ein parshat nedarim tzricha mumche. But not the
פרשת נדרים. parshat nedarim. אלה מועדי ה', elei moadei Hashem, the keyword
is אלה, elei, like זה הדבר. zeh hadavar Only these are the
ones that אשר תקראו אותם asher tikre'u otam that requires a בית
דין beis din to sanctify. Not שבת and not the פרשה parsha
that comes afterwards, not מטות. Mattos. The role of התרת נדרים hataras
nedarim is not done by a similar body as the body that
sanctifies the new moon. The body that sanctifies the new moon is
a בית דין beis din. of מומחים, mumchim, of experts. And the
body that can annul vows is not a בית דין beis din
of מומחים, mumchim, okay, אפילו בית דין הדיוטות, afilu beis din hedyotos,
even by a בית דין beis din of הדיוטות. hedyotos. So the
גמרא Gemara. says one minute, how could you say you don't need
experts? והא בפרשת נדרים ראשי המטות כתיב, v'ha b'parshat nedarim rashei hamattos
kesiv, it says ראשי המטות, rashei hamattos, which seems like people of
stature, experts. So אמר רב חסדא ואיתימא רבי יוחנן ביחיד מומחה, amar
Rav Chisda v'itema Rabbi Yochanan b'yachid mumche, back to where we were.
יחיד מומחה, yachid mumche, it's true, ראשי המטות rashei hamattos is what
you do when you do it by a יחיד, yachid, when you
do it by an individual. Okay, that's ראשי המטות. rashei hamattos. And
בית דין beis din of הדיוטות hedyotos is when you do it
by a בית דין. beis din The תורה's Torah telling you a
בית דין beis din of מומחים mumchim is what you need for
קידוש החודש, kiddush hachodesh, but for התרת נדרים hataras nedarim you don't
need a בית דין beis din. of מומחים, mumchim, you know, you
can even do it with a בית דין beis din, of הדיוטות.
hedyotos. Now the key question comes here. So that's a very nice
לימוד. limmud. As opposed to like a זה הדבר zeh hadavar. זה
הדבר, we have it by the juxtaposition with the אשר תקראו אותם,
asher tikre'u otam, which helps us also in terms of understanding that
it's a body of a בית דין. beis din אשר תקראו אותם,
asher tikre'u otam, right? Similar to the בית דין beis din that
makes the new month you have a בית דין beis din that
annuls vows. It's also not a judicial בית דין beis din like
I said before, although by the new moon it can't be קרובים.
Anyway, but it's a similar body, but אלה elei is telling you
it doesn't have to be מומחה. mumche, If you need a מומחה,
mumche? then that would be by case of a יחיד. yachid. Now
here comes the key question, who is a מומחה? mumche Okay, so
you could have said that a מומחה mumche was like the מומחה
mumche by בית דין Beis Din, of a new month. And the
בית דין of making the new month is a מומחה mumche with
סמיכה, smicha, with going back to the סמיכה smicha that goes back
to משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, right? It's why we don't nowadays sanctify
the month based on eyewitness testimony, we don't have the סמיכה smicha
that goes all the way back, we don't have such a בית
דין. So as such, if that's the מומחה mumche of the בית
דין, then logically when we say by נדרים nedarim also there's a
distinction between מומחה mumche, and not מומחה, mumche the מומחה mumche would
be only somebody that has סמיכה. smicha. That's a possible reading, but
רמב"ם Rambam says no, that the מומחה mumche that is meant here
is not somebody with סמיכה, smicha, the מומחה mumche that is meant
is somebody that is like גמיר וסביר, gamir v'sabir, somebody right, who
knows the הלכה, halacha, who can understand the issues, etc. Okay, you
know, that's the type of a מומחה mumche that is being referred
to here, and like it's not the exact same מומחה mumche. as
the role is sanctifying the new month, that needs a certain power
that derives from. משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu that means one type of
מומחה. mumche If the role is being מתיר matir a נדר neder
then that power is
the significance of מומחה mumche makes it a different significance in this
capacity and it's not about this type of סמיכה semicha going to
משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. So if you take a look at the
ר"ן, Ran he says here at the top. He says like this.
Very top line of ע"ח עמוד ב'. Ayin-Chet amud bet. ומדמה הכא
דיחיד מומחה דשרו נדרים דכסמוך כמומחה של מפי השם. U'madmeh hacha d'yachid
mumche d'sharu nedarim de'kasamuch k'mumche she'mi'pi Hashem. It's סמוך, samuch, דהיינו משה
ואהרן, de'inu Moshe v'Aharon, דלית הפסק בין זה לזה. de'leit hefsek bein
zeh l'zeh. אלא דמפי השם צריכים שלושה מומחים ונדרים סגי ביחיד. Ela
de'mi'pi Hashem tzrichim shlosha mumchim u'nedarim sagi b'yachid. אבל הרמב"ם ז"ל כתב
פרק י"ב
מהלכות שבועות דכל שהוא רב מובהק מתיר יחידי.
Aval ha'Rambam zal
kasav perek yud-bet me'hilchos shvuos de'chol she'hu rav muvhak matir yachidi. He
has to be like an expert. Okay, now, it's not enough to
be גמיר וסביר gamir v'savir to know the הלכות, halachos, because גמיר
וסביר gamir v'savir I just said that before, but I was being
a little bit loose, because גמיר וסביר gamir v'savir to know the
הלכה, halacha, you need even in case of a בית דין of
three, right? The ר"ן Ran says look, the ר"ן Ran asks another
question on the עמוד א'. amud aleph. If you don't need מומחה
mumche for בית דין of three, why can't I have just three
completely ignorant people?
That's what we do
for התרת נדרים hataras nedarim and that actually is true on ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but let's bracket the ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. If
you're going with a real נדר neder. to get a התרה, you
don't take three people who know nothing, right? One person on the
בית דין has to know what they're doing. So the ר"ן Ran,
basically says, he says, I mean, you know, you could say this
slightly differently, but I think what the ר"ן Ran is basically getting
at is, if somebody knows nothing and you have a בית דין
made up of three people who know nothing... exactly. Then it's not
that somehow they're by... by
qualifications they're
invalid. It's they're not doing an act of התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim.
An act of התרת נדרים, hataras nedarim, it's not defined as the
act if you don't know what you're doing, right? You have to
be able to assess and analyze or whatever, and if you just
are just saying words without actually knowing what you're... you know, what
role you're doing and how you're doing it, then it's not even
an act of התרת נדרים. hataras nedarim. So even in a case
of three, at least one of them has to really know and
he has to then be able to explain to the other two
so that they at least are, like he says, so you see,
I'd asked him this and because I've asked him this, he now
really never would have wanted to take it, so really it was
בטל and now let's all say מותר לך. mutar lach. So the
other two... so the other two
understand, right? Okay, but one person has to know. If you don't
know, then what you're doing is meaningless. So what's the additional requirement
by יחיד מומחה? yachid mumche? It's not enough to know and be
an expert. So if we skip to the end of the ר"ן,
Ran he says the
following.
He says... One minute. One
minute.
Okay, so here's the question. You see on the right-hand margin where
it says דף ח' עמוד ב' daf chet amud bet in the
brackets by the ר"ן Ran. in the right-hand margin? Do you have
that? Maybe you have a different גמרא Gemara than I... a different
edition than I do. You see where it says the פירוש הרא"ש
perush ha'Rosh on the left-hand side? The line by the פירוש הרא"ש,
perush ha'Rosh, you have that? Maybe. So go about like four lines
above that in the beginning of the line... on the right, which
says ביחיד מומחה. b'yachid mumche. Okay? But
do you see where it says רבינו שמואל וכתב בפרק יין נסך?
Rabbeinu Shmuel v'kasav b'perek Yayin Nesech? Right? כלשון זה. k'lashon zeh. הכא
נמי ביחיד מומחה. hacha nami b'yachid mumche. So what's a יחיד מומחה?
yachid mumche? בקי בגמרא. baki b'Gemara. כלומר רב מובהק. klomar rav muvhak.
וכבר כתבתי זה בפרק המדיר. u'kvar kasavti zeh b'perek ha'madir.
Okay,
somebody who's like an expert rabbi, who knows like ש"ס. Shas. וקשיא
לי, u'kashya li, אי לא בעי מומחה אלא גמיר וסביר, ei lo
ba'ei mumche ela gamir v'savir, if all מומחה mumcheh means is somebody
that really knows the הלכה halacha here, היכי הוי סבירא ליה לרבי
זירא דרב הונא לא מצי שרי נדרא ביחיד? heichi havay sevira leih
l'Rabbi Zeira de'Rav Huna lo matzi sharei nidra b'yachid? So there's a
גמרא Gemara, he quoted about where... where somebody thought that רב הונא
Rav Huna might not have the ability to מתיר matir a נדר.
neder So if all being מתיר matir a נדר by יחיד yachid
means, means being an
expert, how could the גמרא have thought that רב הונא Rav Huna
would lack that capacity? ונראה לי דכיון דראשי המטות כתיב, v'nira li
d'keivan d'rashei ha'matos ksiv, so the ר"ן Ran says it's not enough
to be an expert. It says ראשי המטות, rashei ha'matos, משמע דהפרת
נדרים נמסרו ליושבים ופרוקים שבדור. mashma de'haforas nedarim nimseru l'yoshvim u'frukim she'ba'dor.
It needs to be the most expert in the generation, like the
גדולים gedolim of the דור. dor. It's not enough that you totally
know this area. You have to be considered amongst the גדולים, gedolim,
like the ראשי המטות rashei ha'matos of the generation. Political leaders?
Well, maybe. Okay, but he's also מובהקים, muvhakim, like the biggest תלמידי
חכמים. talmidei chachamim. I mean, you're right, we're translating. In the גמרא,
it's in the תורה, Torah, it's a political leader. וסבירא ליה לרבי
זירא דרב הונא. v'sevira leih l'Rabbi Zeira de'Rav Huna. לאו בר הכי
הוא. lav bar hachi hu. He thought that רב הונא Rav Huna
wasn't in that category. אסיקנא אני אומר Asikna ani omer דלמאן דסבר
דלא בעינן סמוך, de-le-man de-savar de-lo ba'inan samuch, as long as you-
if you don't need somebody who has סמיכה semichah from משה רבינו,
Moshe Rabbeinu, okay, then כל שהוא רב מובהק בדורו ומתיר יחידי, kol
she-hu rav muvhak be-doro u-matir yechidi, then as long as you're just
the expert rabbi of your generation. Exactly. As long as you're the
גדול הדור. gadol ha-dor. Right. So you don't have to be a
סמוך, samuch, but you could be- be the גדול הדור. gadol ha-dor.
Okay.
You can't go to any little rabbi.
Right. Right. So he says, on the one hand, you don't have
to be like the expert that one could imagine in the time
of like- the- that ever was. Right? You don't have to be
an un- it's a relative status. It's not like nobody nowadays could
ever be a מובהק, muvhak, could ever be a- that's not true.
We could- there- it's- it's relative. But nevertheless, it's- you gotta be
in the top 1% right of whatever your generation is. So it's
sort of- three- there are three ideas. One idea is that it
has to be סמיכה semichah from משה רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, which nobody
has.
Like- right? Like- right.
Like- like- like- some מומחה like בית דין של קידוש החודש. Beis
Din shel kiddush ha-chodesh. That we're going to rule out. But even
if it means expert, there are three ideas. One is just knowing
the laws of נדרים nedarim and being an expert, general, you know,
big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Okay. That seems like that's not enough
because even on a normal בית דין, people have to know what
they're doing. So you could maybe say it has to be a
little bit more than that or whatever. But anyway, one is just
sort of to say like a big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. That's
not enough for the ר"ן. Ran The other is to say that
you need to be
like as great as the וילנא גאון. Vilna Gaon. Okay. That there's
some absolute standard that nobody will ever reach. Okay. That's also not
enough. And the ר"ן Ran says it's a middle level. Every generation
has its מומחים. mumchim. The מומחים mumchim are the מומחים mumchim of
the generation. Okay. So every generation there are some people that could
be מתיר יחידי, matir yechidi, but they're a very small number in
every generation. Alright. So now let's just read a little bit more,
try to keep our full דף ahead here. Let's get back to
the גמרא. The גמרא says like this. So that's the end, that's
the הלכה. halacha. There's three הגדות, haggadot, but the three הגדות, haggadot,
one of them has to know what he's doing and or a
יחיד מומחה
yachid mumcheh has to be knowing what they're doing.
Or whatever. The ר"ן Ran quotes, it's not in our גמרא, but
the ר"ן earlier quotes it based on other גמרות. Gemaras. Okay. And
like I said, the logic is because you need otherwise they're not
doing anything meaningful. One has to know and then you have to
be able to explain to the others then the others have to
be able to understand.
Meaning they have to be...
One has to be, yes, he has to actually, one's to be
like גמיר וסביר gamir ve-savir and the others has to just be
סביר. savir. One has to know and be able- and understand, and
the others have to be able to understand when it's explained.
Meaning they have to be...
Based on other גמרות. Gemaras. Exactly. It's the ר"ן earlier on like
דף כ"ו daf chaf vav or something. I can show it to
you. Okay. It's referred to here.
Because my big question, and I mean I'm really serious about this.
How do we get around doing what we do on ראש השנה?
Rosh Hashanah? Like, you know, sometimes in בתי דינים, batei dinim, the
guys like literally can barely like get a word of Hebrew out.
Right? And like- so is that...
It's a good question. So for a lot of people that's- you
know, it- it- it- it- it- it really isn't doing anything. You're
not מפר הנדר. meifer ha-neder. You're certainly not looking for a פתח.
pesach. You know, so for some people what's really more important is
just the fact that you're מוסר מודעה moseir moda'ah for the future.
You know, it's not true- a lot- what you're saying is- according
to a lot of פוסקים, poskim, it's not a real התרת נדרים.
hataras nedarim.
Okay. Even could it not be just that the words are actually
written out for them to read? What? In other words they are
reading the correct words, right? Right.
And maybe look and you could claim that if we're doing it
based on the idea of חרטה charatah and not on the idea
of פתח, pesach, it's enough to just have remorse, then everybody could
be גמיר וסביר, gamir ve-savir, then you don't need to go through
a process. We don't go through a process of analyzing had you
done this, would you have what- whatever. Right? Everybody can understand if
you're- if you're remorseful about doing it, then we can annul the
vow. Maybe that's enough גמיר וסביר. gamir ve-savir.
Right, but the problem would be that the people- like because I
mean I see this too- the people are just saying words in
Hebrew right that they don't understand.
Right. So everybody is told to say the- people are told to
say them in whatever language they understand. It's a problem. You're right.
It's a problem. Okay. But you're right. What is the level of
גמיר וסביר? gamir ve-savir? If you say that you don't have to
be a פותח poteach with a פתח, pesach, you can just go
straight to חרטה, charatah, which is essentially what we do. Right? You're
also not being פורט הנדר, poreit ha-neder, which is something we also
discussed. So there's a real question about whether you can- whether it
really counts or not. Okay. I guess we really only have like
two minutes so rather than start a new topic we will just
end here. Now we can't be a full two דף ahead, but
okay, we'll worry about it tomorrow.